all right welcome to the idea cafe game
the idea cafe where we are answering
what is my experience in game be been
like so far who would like to start
Jubilee you never go first I think you
should go first
all right it's like I don't want to go
first because I can't think of what I'm
answering so my experience I want to
like talk about I don't want it to just
be the happy I want it to be both so my
experience Brett just drives my
experience so far in game B I was so
happy to have found the game beat
community having other people who also
care about the planet but like in this I
don't know like like big stuff has to
shift for first stuff to happen my
language skills are a little off at the
moment um was a huge breakthrough for me
I mean I've been working in this space
without the language for years but
feeling very isolated and very alone in
it because you can't explain your idea
and you're not surrounded by people who
even want to understand the idea it is a
very isolating place to be in and so
encountering game B for the first time
in September of 2019 it felt like I had
come home like I'd found the people the
community that was doing this work and
wanting to do this work I also have
found that the conversations I have had
both individually one-on-one and the
group conversations have been huge like
I feel like the pieces are falling into
place the vision I had seen before ever
encountering game B and now it's kind of
like unfolding in this way that only I
can see it but I think other people feel
it in their own way in their own that
like the right people are coming on
board at the right time with the right
tools and the right ideas for together
tech to happen and every time it feels
like it's gonna like fall apart it's
actually the thing that helps it stick
together more and helps it yes like
learn at a deeper level at least for me
individually I'm learning that but
there's also it's the place where I now
can encounter tension that is like the
perfect amount of tension for me it's
like alright when when somebody does
something in this space that I don't
like I know it's for me to learn from
and so learning it has been what happens
like I I kind of knew how to create game
B before her encountering game B but not
really because I wasn't playing it with
other people it was just in my head it
was like one person's idea of how the
world can can be a better place and so
encountering other people has helped me
figure out the road towards playing it
with other people how do we create an
omni wind society society and anti-bible
in a society and I am having a lot of
fun but I think that that in and of
itself can be triggering for people like
I just had a conversation with someone
yesterday who's clearly not happy with
the fact that I'm not willing to learn
discord or I'm not willing to to read an
article or I'm like I'm only gonna do
what is fun and easy for me that is the
only thing I'm doing because that is
what keeps me have sustained energy and
quite frankly I'm doing a lot like
especially in the game B's phase I'm
like here's the list of everything I'm
doing and I'm not doing a single thing
that I don't find fun and engaging and I
think that actually that is how we
sustain ourselves on the course to gain
B and I'm just gonna ramble on for the
next minute if I keep going so I'm gonna
end it there we would like to go next
I can go next
yeah there's two parts of this question
isn't there there's there's game be the
brand if you like so you know the
Facebook group and all of that stuff and
then there's game be the actual meta
game you know the actual idea space
exploring stuff so yeah there's two
parts to it so I guess I'm going to get
on your song to give two answers and so
the second bit first of all though that
the game be the framing and the
involving of complexity theory alongside
history alongside behavior economic
Jeremy like they're trying to bring all
of these different disciplines into it I
think there's a lot of parallels with
meta modernism as well even though they
they seem to try and want to stay in
different cameras but whatever I did the
capacity of the frames was I guess what
attracted me to Gambia I mean I came to
this arena via the zeitgeist movies and
The Venus Project and quite a lot of
conspiracy sort of stuff and
I mean though that's still very much a
part of my personal threat but but it's
not helpful right and it puts a lot of
people off whereas the game be
structures frameworks narratives
whatever you want to call them are
extremely neutral right they're entirely
apolitical they're entirely a religious
they are but they're you know they they
they sort of sit outside of all of that
which I which was what was has got
appeal to me in terms of the actual
game B thing itself right now the
mimetic tribe is a different is a
different issue right the Facebook group
and the t-shirts and made me laugh that
thing of the t-shirt sale that was very
funny you know all of that kind of stuff
that's a different story but
nevertheless I must say I've got a lot
out of it personally I mean as jublee is
already said you know these
conversations that I've been fortunate
enough to be involved in as a direct
consequence of the mimetic tribe that is
game be a hugely important part of my
life I mean a I learn a lot from B they
fill a part way fill anywhere a couple
of the important needs that I have you
know I I have really probably one person
that I know well in my life that I can
have these kinds of conversations with
and apart from that really it's it's you
know I live in different worlds in in
some ways to a lot of people I know best
so you know it is also there and my and
just like Jubilee I don't want it to be
all
[Music]
cotton candy and flowers because I do
think that there is a tendency within
the mimetic community ends well no no
just the mimetic music's gaem be the
broader thing is not restrict anyway
it's a much bigger thing that so there's
a tendency I think to go up our own
asses basically a little bit you know
what I mean talk around and around
around make things way more complicated
and way more intellectual and blah blah
blah then they sometimes need to be I
mean don't make me Ron there's a place
for that but I think there is a tendency
to talk and talk and talk and talk and
talk and talk and talk and look at
things through a million different
lenses but never actually get around to
fucking doing anything you know what I
mean going out and actually building
those relationships with real people who
live right in front of you you know what
I mean actually doing that stuff seems
to be has been disappointingly absent
from it it's too theoretical I think
sometimes I think that's probably enough
all right Cara and Brett quickly Kyra
I'll go what is my game be the
experience been so far like both Jubilee
and Eric no Jubilee I could totally
relate to that phrase of feeling like
coming home like being able to come in
and participate in these conversations
once a week you know there are that it
feeds include several needs for me that
I have not been able to get met anywhere
else and so being able to participate in
that is something that I truly
appreciate and being able to engage in
conversations that I wouldn't otherwise
get to participate in my day to day life
because the people that I know just
don't think in these terms is so
incredibly wonderful and you know I'm
also in that space of I don't have the
energy to commit to things that I don't
enjoy and so it's like I come and
participate because I enjoy it and that
sustains me and that keeps me wanting to
come back it's not doing things because
I have to it's doing them because I want
to participate in them and I want to be
a part of them and that's something that
feels really positive and good and again
with the you know the negative app you
know the negative aspects you know
there's some interesting things that
some interesting feelings that I've had
coming up the with a lot more in in the
game be Facebook group which isn't game
B itself but it's one of the things you
know it's a structure you know seeing
more admins being added and more
structure being put in place that well
that's a good thing there's also this
part of me that's like has some
interesting feelings about it and I was
this morning listening to John Verve a
key and Jordan halls second conversation
some I think it was back in February and
I'll probably bring that up more
later in the conversation but it's how
you know how the the group evolves and
you know participating in it and and I
don't experience the same frustration
that I've heard other people experience
of like they're not being action because
what I see is a lot of distilling of
ideas getting to them to a place where
we can take them out and talk to people
who are not familiar with the subject
and because it's like each time I have a
conversation I wrap my mouth and my head
around how to talk about these subjects
more and distill them into easier things
to talk about and so that that that
particular need that's one of those
needs that's getting met by these groups
is it's like I have a lot of these ideas
but I don't know how to you know I don't
know how to take John for Vicki's 50
hour series and explain it to somebody
fairly quickly and so it's in these
conversations that I'm able to to learn
how to distill them and and to really
understand and embody what the ideas
mean versus just that being an idea in
my head and yeah that's what I got so
far I'm sure more will come up as the
conversation progresses thanks Kyra you
wanna share Brent I cannot meet you
years myself
Brent you can oh sorry I forgot I was
muted if you're gonna do that you know
allowed to speak that's returning you've
done your birdie speech but I was muted
anyways hmm
hmmm I like all your guys's stories
isn't it's nice and helpful in different
parts of it are similar to my own
as you know I'm in exile of gave me so I
have mixed mixed feelings my experiences
have been good and bad it's exactly what
I expected from the beginning because I
knew what it was I liked Jubilees story
because it's so recent you know it's
like four months ago still and it's so
it's fresh and it's new and there is a
lot of exciting content you know through
game be and peep and good people to talk
to so it makes sense for it to be
exciting and something you want to
commit to right of course my perspective
is not really discovering game B in the
same way it's sort of studying these
types of things for almost a deck or
over a decade and and uh sort of working
on meta modernism as an emerging
discourse and then at certain points
they it kind of intersects and clashes
with game B right so that's that's sort
of my path here hmm yeah I guess I'm
still a little bit bitter about the
situation because like it creates this
kind of kind of schism where I'm still
in I'm still in this group and other
groups
but not in the Facebook page right so
the this is like you know not to get
into my personal case but this is
indicative of some of the kind of
inconsistencies and pathologies of how
the discourse works how people
communicate how they how they moderate
what what beliefs and preferences they
have that affect their worldview and how
they compartmentalize and package those
things I think there's
lots to be teased out here um today
today is relevant you know to to this
issue to because Jim Rudd is voting for
Biden today and you know he seems pretty
excited and and secure about that choice
um basically because he's afraid of
Bernie what what Bernie represents
potentially and you know there's not
much not much we can do about that at
the end of the day what else what's the
question if you don't mind because it
links directly smart you'll talk to you
about brain because it's something I
left out of my own thing and that's the
poor way in which conflict disputes
would ever have have been handled as
another is another thing bar again I
think it's really really really
important I mean I do it all the time
myself conflate the game be Facebook
group we've gained be right and you know
it's it's really important to remember
that these are distinct things and so
whatever if whatever the pros and cons
of the Facebook group are not
necessarily strengths and weaknesses of
the game be seen itself right I mean
that is very much bigger and you know
was exiled from Facebook group yeah not
game be that would be an impossible game
be itself would be impossible sorry ray
it's all right it's the time like yeah I
want I want to agree with that a hundred
percent like I agree part way but it is
a question at the end of the day of the
people who actually coined the term the
metaphor and who are more or less you
know curating and and and leading that
charge so I have more of an issue with
that than I do with the game be idea
itself and the community itself hmm
well but to bring up the point of
several of the people who participated
from what kind of the very beginning of
game B have left the game be Facebook
group okay so like Jordan Hall and
Bonita Roy aren't in the Facebook group
anymore okay name is well haven't seen
Daniel ages yeah I mean it was ever in
there I see yeah you wants for talks
time yeah yeah yeah so these things are
these things are in flux you know it's
kind of experimental um I don't know if
then just leaving the Facebook group you
know addresses the the issue I think
mmm-hmm I've no doubt that like like
they themselves are still struggling
with this in different ways on their end
you know and I think I think that's like
I'm not happy about that
so yeah things ones sorry but it also
underlines the fact that the game be
Facebook is not game be right these
people have not abandoned game be
they've banded the Facebook group yeah
and and I would I would carry my
arguments over to say like I think I
think that's a mistake
I think that's part of the problem
because whatever whatever Jordan Hall
and Bonita I are doing now they're still
being themselves and they're still doing
good stuff and doing what I think are
bad stuff they're just avoiding the
problem what is the problem what in a
sentence
I mean they're yeah there's a couple
dimensions to it like one is that they
just quit when things got difficult uh
another is sort of the the the premises
that led up to that right so if if
they're entrenching their positions
whether it's about politics or race and
the solution for them personally was
just to kind of retreat nobody really
gets any clear answers and like they're
they're they're abandoning the kind of
roles but that they built up for
themselves and and I wouldn't do that if
it was me
and given my given myself in my position
I'm still showing up to to challenge
wherever I think of people are going
wrong I think it goes back to you one of
the points that Jubilee made of you know
part of what makes or part of what
allows me to put the energy into game be
that I put into it is by by sticking
with the things that I can that I can
actually put energy into and so and it's
interesting because I was listening to
you bring back that interview that I was
listening to you this morning Jordan
Hall was talking about the we the
founders dilemma are the innovators
dilemma or something like that of you
know it's like the person who comes in
and does all of the innovation doesn't
necessarily you come in and you have all
of this innovation and you want to keep
that innovation as part of the
organization that gets built but that
work but inherently the organization is
sort of a limitation to the ability to
innovate and so it might be that you
know people are coming in and they're
like okay this is this is as far as I
can go with this group and and still
care and want to participate in the
overall movement and so you know it's
not funny that I don't you know there's
part of me that agrees but then also
that part of me is I would say a
holdover of gaming a mentality of once
you've committed to something you have
to stick it through no matter what and
if you don't then there's some of you
have some character flaw and I think one
of the things about game B is you're
gonna bounce around you're gonna go okay
this I'm gonna stay in this this thing
and well I have reached my you know
until I have learned what I need to
learn here and then I'm going to move
over here and being able to move between
areas it's one of the things I think
that appeals to me about the game B
ethos is it's not
they fronted a values of once you've
committed to something that's your role
and you stick it out and granted I still
had strong emotions when I read with
bonitas post that she was leaving of
like for being abandoned yeah but kind
of going oh wait a minute you know she's
going where her energy can serve the
most he can be of most service and I
understand where you're coming from
Brett so balance because you have like
the people who started game beam a game
B is a very hard to understand and easy
to understand concept at the same time
right the game becomes after game a is
so easy that like right you can tone
that right like you can't actually even
if you were one of the founders and the
Facebook group is very much Jim ruts
version of game B and how he thinks it
should go right and in fact it was
actually like it's what happened when it
was in sport mode and it went off and he
started it he's been maintaining it and
now it's at a thousand and and like it's
I have and this is very different
because because the person didn't create
acoustic neuromas Kristin Toma is the
type of brain tumor that I had and I was
in this Facebook group that I got kicked
out of because I questioned the mods
that were like they were like only
scientific stuff but then whenever
anyone had a surgery they were like you
have do would you like us to pray for
you so we'd have like prayer circles and
then so I was like why can't people talk
about essential oils that we're having
prayer right like you don't even ask if
someone wants you to pray for them and
it was like well if you don't like it
you could leave I was like okay then you
should change the name of this Facebook
group to whatever your name is is
acoustic neuroma right not just acoustic
neuroma and I don't feel like that's how
Jim Wright in any ways is running game
if the game be but their way you create
something in the world that is game be
it has to be let go of it has to be like
a little bit it runs with itself and
also like how much do you hold on to it
and have it run your
vision and how much is it its own child
that you know what I mean runs and I
think there's a balance especially in
the beginning where but at the same time
everyone who is encountered baby has
their own version of game B and the fact
that it's based on song sovereignty and
Omni win means that we all kind of get
to run with it in our own way and then
find ways to come together and do that
but the Facebook group is the easiest
way to do that and so it has the most
power and it has the most like it has
the most people in it right like there
might be more on Twitter but not in one
place it's not like you can't have a
thousand people on Twitter having a
conversation it just doesn't work
doesn't work on Facebook but I think you
know because I I come more from the meta
modern kind of zeitgeist it's such a big
topic just like game B is I think I
think it has to be handled carefully um
but I encourage people you know to
pursue it with the same enthusiasm at
least because it's so related you know
like like I I write about systems change
which is supposed to be the major kind
of premise of getting from game a to
game be like how does that happen
what does it look like and these are
huge discourses right it goes way beyond
game I want to support the what I see is
the good aspects of game be but also be
critical of what I see is the obvious
limitations and flaws right it's a very
silicon valley-based a kind of worldview
right and and you know it's it's got
different alignments than the
progressive movement at the end of the
day and
I think that's a mistake I think that
that mistake happens because of devoted
interests into some of these discourses
and end the commercial aspect of it that
it's a you know sort of locks us back in
the game a and when I talk to Jim right
like this came this came up because we
talked about funding about the Santa Fe
Institute and you know he was saying how
like like for anybody it's difficult to
get funding there's certain hoops that
have to jump through there's certain
path dependencies and you know my major
injunction there - Jim was like uh you
know as someone who has researched it
Marxism is actually a complexity science
right
and then he said that one of one of the
head guys at Santa Fe you know
identifies as a Marxist so so Jim likes
to you know entertain that diversity to
a certain extent so that's that's a good
thing but but the point was more about
funding because I was kind of pressing
him on you know like how how research
gets funded and how that relates to his
blind spot right because he acknowledges
he has a blind spot in sociology and
that's mainly what I've studied like I'm
have a very interdisciplinary background
but I I try to anchor it in sociology
because it's such an important discourse
and it's so underrated right so it's
kind of pressing them like on the fact
that you know most of the time the think
tanks aren't funding the best research
right it's it's not exclusive to Santa
Fe Institute it's this is a problem of
all research of universities of think
tanks you know a lot of things that are
cutting edge get done for free and I
think that's something the game be
community can understand quite well but
it still becomes a kind of
self-fulfilling prophecy on their own on
their own terms right because the the
complexity Institute the Santa Fe
Institute which is a complexity Research
Center
Hasnat but via via gym rat I would say
because because there's other people
involved like Michael Garfield uh who
are great and they're much more open
they're much much more progressive uh
and there's there's a kind of higher
synthesis of all the complexity we're
talking about here so mm-hm so my
criticism is just that um you know
whether it's whether it's due to the
funding pressures or something else the
the blind spots are not being funded so
the answers that they get are of a
certain nature and and contribute to a
certain logic right so it just keeps us
stuck in the kind of pattern that we're
trying to escape depending on Santa Fe
Institute I don't even know who they
were so it's one piece of the puzzle
though it's important like like Jim was
the the chair for a number of years so
so he had a lot of influence can I just
push back on the assertion that game be
is a Silicon Valley kind of perspective
because I just I've heard this criticism
before or not and I disagree with it I
think that is in the eye of behad in the
eye of the beholder that criticism
because game be at least my take on game
B is that it's grounded in all kinds of
stuff right I mean including John Vevey
Keyes retrospective on you know wisdom
cultivation going back thousands of
years yeah it's grounding all of that as
well it's grounded in Jung is is
grounding it's grounded in
what's-his-name prj you know it's
grounded in mathematics it's grounded in
complexity theory it's grounded in
evolutionary biology you know what I
mean it's grounded in all of these
domains simultaneously I think to label
it as Silicon Valley's perspective is to
actually quite profoundly misunderstand
what the game be notion is all about
that is that is a perfect example of
confusing the mimetic tribe and all of
the projections that go onto that with
the thing itself right which
nebulus this is the problem right when
he gives something a name a meta
modernism has a massive advantage over
gain B in its name and that meta
modernism the name it sounds like it's a
big thing right it's complicated there's
lots to learn about it you know and it's
hard to gain any sort of level of
expertise you know you've got to be
studious it sort of implies that the
name whereas game B it sounds so sweet
so simple so fun so easy right and so
the variety and the complexity in the
interactions between all of these
multiple things in which it's branded
because it's not just Jordan Hall and
Danny American burger and Bonita Roy and
Jamba vague you know it's loads and
loads and loads of other people have
contributed to conversation well and
that constantly broadens the grounding
from which it comes and so it's a you
know it's an ever-evolving thing so yeah
I think that's a really limiting critic
I think it's a false criticism and I
think it's one which profoundly
misunderstands what the thing is or was
is actually all about
yeah just quick very quickly like let's
try to meet halfway on that because I
think those are valid counter points and
it's certainly more than a Silicon
Valley thing but but I think it's
inescapable the connection like there's
definitely people involved that are not
anywhere near Silicon Valley mm-hmm
but and there and there's critiques of
Silicon Valley a culture and techno
optimism separate from game B E which
are much more relevant and salient but
but I'm saying we shouldn't miss the
connection right like like Jordan Hall
was a tech entrepreneur that's how he
made his money that's why we're
listening to him today you know he's a
self-taught kind of thought leader in
these spaces but at the end of the day
he became financially independent from
tech entrepreneurship and that's that's
where those guys live that it informs a
lot of the thinking it's it's it's a
little bit inescapable so I'll try to
meet halfway I'll just point out that
Jordan Hall does not live in Silicon
Valley but he still lives in California
but not in Silicon Valley don't they
live close though like Diego okay no no
a bunch of them live all live down in
San Diego as far as I know
but one of the conversations one of the
things that was on the interview that I
was talking that I was listening to this
morning was that one of the things that
is true is Silicon Valley being what it
is it in many senses at the heart of the
meaning crisis because there are a bunch
of people who are you know taking game a
to its limit and then realizing oh shit
this doesn't give me the meaning in life
that I thought it was and so then it
would make sense that some of the ideas
would be emerging out of sort of the
Titans of game a kind of coming in and
going oh wait a minute like I played
that game the absolute best you can play
it and my life wasn't any better I don't
have any more meaning in my life so what
do we do now so like it makes sense to
meaning that Silicon Valley would be
sort of one of one of the epicenters of
this because there is so much excess so
much you know being able to play game a
to its limit lots of small driven people
yeah yes and so when you have driven
people who go wait a minute
I can't you know this the promise that I
was you know the thing I was promised
didn't come to fruition
of course and if we're gonna look at you
know where things are coming from and I
I'm still reminded of a meme that I saw
in the game group that said if you're
participating in Game a and you haven't
experienced a nexus if you're
participating in game B and you haven't
experienced an existential crisis yet
you're doing it wrong yeah and you know
I mean that's been my experience was
that I was fully on the game a track and
then like life happened and it was like
wait a minute
there's no meaning any of this and I
experienced that full-on existential
crisis and then had to you know sort of
crawl my way out of it and you know game
B is one of the places that I found like
people who are kind of going who are
thinking the same thing like looking
around and going everything I ever
learned about life and about meaning is
wrong
and can I talk to you about this because
otherwise I just feel like I'm crazy
because other people are like well I
don't know what are you talking about
I get just plenty of satisfaction out of
what I might I'm doing okay then I'm not
[Music]
soft top pick up a little bit but it
begs the question are they actually
experience that's experiencing
satisfaction or are they have they just
convinced themselves that they are you
know it is great some people experience
satisfaction I think happiness and
satisfaction for me anyway it comes from
knowing who you are finding the right
people to be around who can see you for
who you are and accept you having a
purpose something you can do and then
having enough resources that you don't I
mean you're not not in poverty those
four things are like when I'm playing
with and I think some people have found
that right some people in Silicon Valley
and whatever have the resources because
they're rich they found their purpose
whatever piece that they're doing they
really enjoy they they the people piece
might be the like they may have found a
connected group of friends that do love
them do accept them the issue is a lot
of times that falls apart because you're
putting on a persona right I'm
pretending to be a Silicon Valley person
I'm pretending to be a rich like
whatever this even if you are actually
rich who feel like you're putting on a
mask to be there you don't really know
who you truly are because all of those
are existential crises right like Who am
I where do I belong what am I here to do
and like how can I get it what do I need
is maybe less of an extra central crisis
like you need that to be able to do the
other three but some of them are happy
but not most of them my I would say my
husband is one of those that's been one
of my problems is like I look at him and
he's just he finds out it he absolutely
loves what he does and he is one of
those people who is so confident in
himself that he can walk into you know
anywhere and be him and for the most
part be himself
and doesn't you know doesn't have to
pretend and so you know I do know it's
possible for some people but I think
most are trying to figure you know are
more in you know the situation I was in
then you know then what I mean there's a
reason that that drug abuse and
everything else a rampant here it's like
everyone there's a tiny group of people
who are happy who are in that space and
happy but the vast majority in that
space aren't happy and the rest of us
are trying to get to that space because
we think it's gonna bring happiness and
then we get there and we have the
existential crisis we're probably not
one of the tiny few like I've come to
happiness from the completely other way
like through existential crisis and
thinking that was maybe somewhat of the
solution but also seen that it wasn't
and got to like I am happy I am deeply
happy I love Who I am I don't put on a
mask for most of my life I don't show up
like other people because of that like I
I look like I don't know what I'm
talking about I talk around things I'm
like right because that's what my brain
does like this is me I don't know what
to do
but showing up as that and then finding
community is so much better than
pretending and finding fake community
because then you're just lose-lose like
even if you find the perfect people who
love you it's not you who are they
loving it's not I think that's one of
the things that I've gotten so much out
of game a is that like I come here and
you guys don't you know don't seem to
bat an eye when I babble on about
something and then somebody takes off on
a different tangent and like I get to
show up exactly as I am here whereas you
know there are other places in my life
where I I still try and put on a mask
and you know and the more that I get to
and then and this is something I've
talked about in a couple of different
groups is the more I get to show up as
myself in one area it allows me to show
up as myself in other areas and that
because it's like okay if I go out there
and
I show up as myself and somebody says
something I know I have this group right
and come back and go okay this is here
Here I am here's the craziness here's
all of the babbling here's all of my
weird ideas and you know and I know that
I will be you know not not rejected so
that's like yeah I haven't turned you
guys all the crazy yet but every crazy
to my husband has a thing he says
there's good crazy and there's bad crazy
you're the good crazy I'm like okay good
you're the only person in the world then
you know you are both sane and crazy by
definition right this is it's very much
a comparative thing and I hope it's okay
I participated in a conversation with
Nick from the game be conversations
group last week and we we migrated to
standing and like the process of that it
was like starting to kind of feel into
some stuff of like oh okay I don't have
to like sit in one place and be static
the whole conversation and so hopefully
it doesn't it's not bothering anybody to
beat for me to kind of be moving around
are you standing right now yeah I am
okay cool I've got a standing desk it
goes up and down with with motors is
awesome yeah I had one of those at my
job but now I'm my laptop is sitting on
a plastic drawer lift it up high enough
funny I need to figure out how to
because I record videos with my youtube
yes less so during these conversations
but when I'm talking into a camera I'd
always feel so like somewhat unnatural
that when I'm walking around my house
myself I come up with all these great
ideas and even a great way of expressing
them and then when I turn on the camera
it goes off but I'm also sitting down
when I turn on the camera and like I
don't actually know anywhere where I can
record in my house where I'm standing up
walking around and it not like it kind
of has to follow me then because if I'm
walking
and moving and doing anyway yes it's
important I think technology is gonna
get us there pretty quickly like like it
already is because we can all be on our
phones right now walking around having
the same conversation so it's really a
choice but I wanted to say actually
because this is kind of a potentially
very interesting topic there's a lot of
research on standing desks and there's
actually a nonprofit called just an org
and if you go to their website I haven't
been to it in in several years now but
when I went to their website they had
tons of research like catalog and
itemized about standing desks and I was
like holy shit like look at how much
research there is on standing desks how
effective they are and whatnot the take
away if there's a lot of information but
the takeaway is that using standing
desks basically adds five years to your
life right that's that's a huge
oversimplification but this is the kind
of language that they use when they draw
conclusions from their studies right and
that's it's it's important in its
salient because most like a lot of
people work behind a desk we have a very
sedentary II kind of office culture
right and especially these economies
industrialized they become more like
that there's more knowledge workers and
it's interesting okay I bring this up
because it's like scientific proof of
kind of a policy decision that should be
made you know and we can talk about the
practicality of it after but but we
should be able to agree on what the
science says about lifespan and and
health and things like this because it's
such it's a difficult switch to make
like I'm sitting right now I I don't
like have a certain discipline with my
standing desk but I do use it from time
to time and always remind myself like
about this truth about this reality that
the evidence is the scientific studies
on it show a very concrete thing right
but
the broader point is how these things
get politicized or just ignored right so
a few years ago I was so excited about
this and I brought it to the ergonomics
advisor at UBC and I've made a little
kind of presentation and showed some of
the research and and and is this her job
keep in mind is to be the ergonomics
advisor to go around at people's offices
and measure desk desk space and still he
shit like this and you know I was just
sure I was kinda I was trying to help
you know I had no personal incentive I
was trying to like uh help UBC adopt a
policy that was actually like
universally positive even if they just
accepted it in kind of PR terms and
didn't spend a dollar they could say
that hey we advocate standing desks this
is kind of a revolution I think most
employees freak out if you took their
chairs away yeah I mean you're a perv
you zombie threat for it yeah you
acknowledge the benefits of it and yet
you spend the majority of your time
sitting at your standing desk and you
would have a standing desk the evidence
is there when like that's not how
science works it's not like one you just
went off on the Santa Fe Institute and
how they're funded by that I'm sorry but
maybe just an org isn't the best place
to go for all of the scientific evidence
as to whether sitting or standing to me
it's a very personal choice no I want to
be sitting or standing having a standing
desk being able to stand and then
choosing when I sit having my UBC my
government anyone my boss be like you
have to stand because it's better for
your body we're gonna get more work out
of you is an invitation to be like hey
everyone could have a standing desk
which is also way more expensive sign
desks are not the same price it's yeah
and so having the ability to like
instead of top-down this is what the
science says is what everyone should do
everyone should be doing what I'm doing
because I came to it through science and
logic is rival risk
is the like brokenness of like I came to
this so everyone should do it instead of
like listen I have this I have this
piece like even when you're like I went
to UBC and I had nothing in it for me
yeah you had been right in it for you
you had being the person to give that to
them right like of course there's
something in it for you but like finding
the truth for you and then living it and
then no I'm actually just stretching you
can do that it's all good it was just
funny because it was like well it was
like I'm not I'm not proposing this in
an authoritarian way though like I'm go
back and watch this video and I'm not
saying you were like everyone should but
the were like no the evidence is there
this is should be policy this should be
what people do instead of an invitation
replicate in it yeah let's let's wallow
through on that point just because all I
was saying was like not trying to you
know draw the conclusion that that we
should have an authoritarian policy but
to set up the and we can unpack this but
just to set up the premise that the
research is there and if we were all to
look we would all agree and it would be
pretty non-controversial is no there's
literally nothing on this planet that is
cyant maybe gravity that is
non-controversial science comes out even
gravity is the biggest mystery on the
planet like what
there is no you you have to like come to
that evidence to say oh you first all
you have to not have a position come hey
let's look at all the evidence and see
is standing or sitting better for the
majority and then who is sitting better
for who is standing better for and what
do you feel like when you're doing it
right and then have that invitation
there's literally nothing in science
that's like cut and dry this is all the
evidence points that this is better or
we would always Commons knew what their
research says you know go to office
chairs calm and have a nice ride there
was two things that came up as you guys
are talking one is I don't remember what
I heard it but there was something that
like 50% of scientific journals journal
articles are are within 5 years proved
false you know so we're talking about
scientific you know an agreement on
scientific journals and then also for me
yeah when I heard the word policy you
know Brett when I heard you say the word
policy what came up in me was this like
I think you guys are completely missing
the point I'm talking about an
intervention recommendation to decrease
the things that are the number one
killers like heart disease and obesity
but but yeah but to make it an option it
has to be policy first for it to be an
option right and then we can get to the
question of costs okay so the policy
okay so there would be a policy that
standing desks are an option for
employees yeah that's what you're saying
it's not like standing desks are the
policy yeah this is also the option of a
standing desk and we recommend them for
these and these and these reasons but
hey if you want to sit you can sit yeah
right I think that but both Jubilee and
I are trying to articulate is not not
saying that you're wrong or but to say
this is our reaction to the way that you
communicated it not that it was
something that was something you know
that you had done you know like not that
we disagree with you necessarily but the
emotion I don't know I I don't wanna
speak for you to believe but that for me
I was trying to express that I was
trying to communicate the reaction I had
to the way that you communicated it and
so not you know not arguing you with you
on that you know one way or the other
but it's like that is those are the
things that those are the things that
percolated to the surface in me when you
talked or when you shared what you were
sharing doesn't mean that I want to
argue with you about the validity of
them either way but that was what
percolated to the surface in me sure
yeah this is also toughened up this
to be gang up on bread day right
abstract like but like your conversation
with Jim right today what it brought up
in me is like I've almost a comments
because it's like I'm on your side I
think Bernie's a much better candidate
both for the world and to be trunk
however I think you've turned more
people off of Bernie than you've turned
on to Bernie no we don't know that I
mean it's like all of the Bernie bros do
it but like you're a Canadian who can't
even vote but it's like you're an idiot
for voting for Biden not vote for Bernie
actually vote on this call but like that
like how much of what are and I'm I know
I do it like I know even talking about
my project I'm like where am I gonna
save the relative like stop are like
under other like stop saying that of
like a text I don't have another thing
to replace it with but coming off with
like that this is black and white and
I'm on the right side therefore if
you're not on my side you're on the
wrong side is so rival rests that it
like can't be game be even if you're on
the right side right like I'm on your
side with birdie but it's like the way
that it's like you're an idiot if you
don't agree with me he's idiotic okay
this is a horrible excuse but Jim's
doing the same thing so I'm just I'm not
I'm not gonna stand for the hypocrisy
that goes both ways when I mean the the
deeper point to me is are we committed
to the process sorry wait where did he
announce that he's gonna be voting for
Biden because his Facebook all over his
face personal all over it and the irony
of this conversation I'm the only one
they can vote and for some reason I
wasn't registered either a Republican or
Democrat so I couldn't vote in it so I
couldn't vote in the primary I just
voted in the you know local issues
weren't where are you cur I'm in Santa
Cruz California
so you vote today ya know just vote I
turned in my I turned in my ballot
yesterday cool is it today is it try
Mary Jay stay it's Super Tuesday
yeah horse Biden would say super
Thursday I didn't realize it was so so
quickly upon us right okay so tomorrow
we get the results then so how does
today like five or six no like 13 or
something I always forget this one then
trickle Oh like it's not even decide I
thought it was decided after super dude
it's like 35% of Delegates American
election is like it's designed for me
[Music]
yeah like what is 81 I think we announce
it and six weeks later we have it and
the Prime Minister can call it whenever
they kind of want to within a certain
and then there's a point where you have
to call them I think it's the fifth year
at the end of the fifth year if you
haven't called 18 emergency you're in
trouble but like six weeks but that's
enough for not three years of like
everyone running and everyone gets up
and then it's not even like the people
get to decide what the questions are in
the debates there's endless debates it's
just so horrific its designs apparently
and this debates about things that are
better than people are based on the
political talking points versus what
people actually care about or want to
hear about so yeah it's it's it's a
disaster I I will agree with that
they've got a really good policy in
Spain where it's a law in fact in Spain
where in the run-up to elections you are
allowed to campaign for one month and
one month only that's it one month of
campaigning up the elections done mm-hmm
i I would add to like I I think
a lot of limitations in in some of his
solutions to these systemic things like
like like it's a bit of a paradox that
he's running on all these small dollar
donations because that's unsustainable
too and it's actually ironic that he's
doing so well when people are so
impoverished like that that's crazy that
he's raising the most money from the
poorest people right like dude do people
stop and think about that because it's
crazy and this is why it's important
that that he has to win because people
can't afford to keep sustaining
progressive politics this way so my hope
for after when however long this takes
to make happen for the US political
system and every political system
elections should be just like you guys
are saying like short and structured and
you know when we talk about getting
money out of politics that what it
should mean is every candidate is has
equal funding and that funding comes
from the state so ultimately from
taxpayers but in a more indirect way
that way like it's not biased at every
step of the way because the media debate
the the mainstream media debates whether
it's CNN or NBC doing them like they're
skewed they're biased they're horribly
structured they produce circuses I mean
I don't think it should be like
Bloomberg and I don't think it should be
all small-dollar donors funding how I
think it should be is a bunch of
candidates have like exact media like
exact equal media exposure you know if
we could agree on that as a kind of
baseline
I think the discourse would be so much
better and candidates though and how do
you feel people that do get the thing is
is that I mean if we talk about the the
idea of stuff as being emergent that
what has emerged you know is
dysfunctional and so learning we're not
going to you know Brett I hear what
you're saying that's not going to happen
and the question you know and the
question is is like how do we
how do you know what it's clear to most
people that what's happening now is
dysfunctional but the question is is
what's gonna emerge next and how do we
influence that we're not going we're not
going to get to a place where everybody
neatly agrees on everything it's more
about the emergent quality and so what
is going to emerge from this I mean it's
interesting to hear your guys's
perspective because from being somebody
who's here in the States the likelihood
of Bernie getting elected is almost
non-existent no that's not true
like from from the like internal from
you know at least one section of the
population is not because of who he is
but because of the DNC not my issue is
not because of who he is it's that he's
not likely to get the nod because of the
DNC and then as a result Trump's gonna
win like that's you know there's a lot
of people who agree that that's what's
going to happen yeah that's what Jim Ron
is voting for and I mean I agree with
your logic to an extent but I also
believe that this time around this time
Bernie can beat the DNC like the
movement I mean we're having a replay of
2016 like there's so many parallels it's
a kind of you know we're out another
kind of bifurcation of the timeline and
last election you know we went down the
darkest timeline and there there's
there's a very good chance Bernie can
win it all
because we have to kind of believe that
the DNC is going to lose this time
around but they are doing everything in
their in their power to stop it here's
the sacred camp Democratic candidate is
that bud and is either sort of sacred
cows I find the sacred cows like this
like if Bernie gets the number of
Delegates if he actually wins through
this whatever frickin hell of a
freakshow long time then he has to win
like 80 percent or something of the
delegates to overcome there this is what
happened with
the issue is with the super-delegates
it's there this is very dysfunctional
thing of there's a whole bunch of people
who are not beholden to who vote who was
voted for they get to choose who they
want and so that's where the super
delegate I mean how does that happen
actually I just recently learned it is
actually something that you were but
that you are voted into but I don't have
I don't fully understand like I know I
don't fully understand how I think I
think through movements by members of
the of the genetic Democratic Party
obviously if you can't be a Republican
you know well who the super-delegates
are going to be yeah yeah it's
complicated yeah there's many ways
there's many types of super-delegates
although we're almost out of time
like yeah that is what we should be
focusing on instead of like yes we
probably all could agree to get money
out of politics but well money's in
politics we're never gonna agree on how
to get money out of politics that like
my brother's project wiki election is
about like how do we know what the fuck
is going on in politics right like how
do we know how do we understand it how
do we say what we want to know and how
do we like how do we compare candidates
regardless of how who has billions of
dollars in the media and who has no
money in the media and what are the
things we care about and how do we know
they're true and then how do we compare
them and those are things we can
actually do with 10,000 people around
$1,000 quite easily instead of like all
of this money and all of this stuff
that's spent on like this person gets in
this person doesn't get in I don't
understand where the Frick
super-delegates come from like
understanding the political politics and
then also having an effect creating what
I've talked about many times not in an
idea cafe a what is it called fantasy
football creating a fantasy government
where like people actually can like
directly say if I was the person here's
what I'd vote for and here's my here's
my group of politicians and are they
voting with me as their constituent or
are they voting with that 1% are they
voting with their stock hole their
shareholders that they have their money
influence with
those things are like real things we
could do to influence politics in six
months to take six months to create
anything but any of that stuff we have
to have money for we have to have the
willpower before before it ever gets
going and concentrating on like well
four of us right one of us could vote
and we can't vote it's like all of our
energy going to like talking about other
people talking I just released a YouTube
video today that is like our governments
aren't the answer
even with wiki lection even with being
able to get people like Bernie in
everything is designed for them not to
be able to create actual solutions that
we need so create the thing to at least
showcase that well we get along with
like creating actual solutions and I'm
sorry I'm wasn't supposed to make anyone
have any closing thoughts politics or
anything I just want to put out you know
like one of the interesting things about
this this election was there there was a
like official ballot thing that came out
like a little booklet that had all the
candidates except for it didn't have any
Republican candidates in it it only had
the Democratic candidates in it and I
don't know why not that it's like Matt
you know not that it mattered well you
know it does matter it's like I'm I'm
lazy I wasn't gonna do the research I
wasn't gonna let go look him up I was
gonna look through this thing and I go
to look in this thing and I'm like wait
there's only two of the three candidates
and I looked in all of the different
sections and Republicans were missing in
every single one I don't know why I you
know but how did that happen like I
don't know
and I I'm not the type of person who's
just going to vote simply based on party
because I just that's just not how I
that's not how I roll but yeah how do we
like how do we get people informed how
do we get people to want to be informed
about politics and how do we get that
participation and I saw an article
recently that said you know then that
this elections going to be won by
participation like if people are willing
support you know it's like and it's
people are willing to vote against or
they're you know that's what's driving
things not what people are voting for
there will be an interesting twist to
the voting system have a - though yeah
you can cast your vote against someone
rather than vote for someone you can
cast your vote against someone you can
cast it for someone or against someone
I've well that's rather than that you
can have ranked choice - right and so
yeah yeah there might be some
complications with that but at least
like in in like if it was me and the
current lineup of candidates I would
pick like Bernie and then and then
Warren right that's a huge difference
from Bernie and Biden and so if a lot of
people vote this way and the data it
does show that most of these other
voters Bernie is their second choice
like like Bernie was Budaj edge but or
their second choice but because we do
judge and endorse Biden you know that
that skews things somewhat who knows how
much but I mean maybe it'll backfire but
but I think rank choice could address
that I do have to go straight yet we all
have to go right away so right Cara all
right so you might have any more closing
comments they were dying to say no
perfect okay bye idea cafe we will see
you next week with whatever topic we
decide to talk about there's actually